We've been talking about single file components,
and it's really time for us to really start diving into it.
Because what we've really done is basically
moved our entire app from index.xml into app.view.
But this code is there's a lot going on here, right?
Especially because there's a lot of logic.
And more importantly, things could be scoped kind of differently.
So it's time to really dive into component-driven development
at this point.
OK, so for what I'm going to do here,
I'm going to delete all the boilerplate inside of our code base
here so that we're not dealing with any boilerplate.
And so let me go ahead and refactor that real quick.
Factor delete boilerplate components.
OK.
So now let's talk about how we actually
create components in view.
As we mentioned, single file components
are basically the way to go.
So let's start with something like the,
let's start with something simple.
Actually, I'm in the wrong directory for this.
Let's go back to the playground.
Because that's the, we'll use the exercise for that.
OK.
Inside of my playground, let's take a look at this one.
So now that we're actually in the build tool, though,
I need to actually make sure I run the right one.
So I'll go back to my playground app and run dev.
And so now that we're running it, there we go.
We see that it automatically refreshed
without me doing anything.
So it's great.
We have the update.
All right.
So let's take a look at what's going on inside of our app here.
There is a lot.
We played around with different concepts.
We talked about lists of numbers.
We talked about this increment thing.
So basically, let's start with the simplest thing, which
is that we have a counter component.
That's like the easiest thing that we could split off
from this at this point.
And so what we can do then is we can say, OK,
let's go into the components folder.
And let's create a new one called counter.view.
So I'm going to go ahead and full screen this
so that it's easier to see, since we don't actually
need to see the live updates right now.
When you're creating a new component, basically we
have our basic building blocks.
We have our script block.
And we have our template block.
We don't have any custom styling right now,
so I'm not going to add anything.
And so let's start moving some stuff over.
So what I would do is I would actually
start by saying, OK, so inside of my script block,
I will export a default object, because this
is what I'm configuring.
And so inside of my data, what do we
have that we want to migrate over?
Well, we care about the count, so that looks good.
The counter title, yeah, that sounds good too.
And we care about the increment amount.
This is good.
And then that's list of numbers not relevant.
OK.
Oh, OK, we have some computer properties
that's relevant for display title and optimized increment
amount.
So actually, none of this is related to anything else,
right, because we have the count, which is here.
We have the display title, which is here.
And the increment amount is here,
meaning we can take this whole block, actually,
and just cut that from the app.view.
And then we can put it here.
And then finally, we have this increment count method
that we're using.
And we're actually not even using the watch,
so we can actually delete this.
And we can cut the methods entire block over.
And then what you'll see that we end up having here
is that we have all of our logic now
scoped to the counter, right?
Nothing that's irrelevant to it is kept to it.
And this is great, right?
And to be clear, this is not a view thing.
React, Angular, we've all been basically thinking this way
as far as keeping our concerns scoped to the same file,
so it's easier for people to understand.
You don't have to jump files as much.
Now, of course, we've got to make sure
we move all the stuff that's related, though,
to the counter app when it comes to 6.0.
So we have that here, here, here, here.
I think I mostly organize it together,
so there's not too much mystery there.
And so I can cut all that and just drop it over here
inside of the template.
And so what you get here now is we have our scoped, JavaScript,
and HTML.
And so now it's a time where we actually
kind of want to see what's going on inside of the app.
And so if you take a look, you'll
notice our counter app is gone.
And that's to be expected, because we've already
moved everything.
But what we haven't done is we haven't actually
called our component.
So how does that actually work?
Well, just like standard JavaScript, what we want to do
is we want to basically import our component.
So we want to import our counter component.
Where are we importing it from?
Well, we're going to move up a directory,
because right now we're in app.view.
We're going to move, oh, wait.
Counter is in the wrong one right now.
It needs to move down here.
OK, so we have our app.view.
And we're going to import counter.
And so this is following the file path directory, where
we have the root directory, which is this flat one right here.
We're going to go up into components.
And then we're going to import counter.view.
So we're going to do.
You'll notice that our extensions are yelling at us,
because why is saying, hey, you imported something,
you never, ever used it.
And so the way we actually register a component inside
of ViewsOption API is, well, there
is an aptly called components option where we can basically
register our counter, just like that.
And then your methods is inside of your computed encounter.
Computed.
Oh, yeah, you're totally right.
So the observation was pointed out here
that my methods, when I copy and pasted,
was copy pasted at the wrong point.
So we should actually move this out.
There you go.
Now that looks much better.
Oh, yeah, that's another thing we'll talk about in a second.
OK, there we go.
We have counter.
This is good.
And then now we need to actually use it.
How do you use it?
Well, it's a custom component.
So whatever we named it, basically, we'll do the trick.
Let's go.
There we go.
There's our counter component.
A couple of things that might be new,
if you haven't really worked with components before,
is that this is what's called a self-closing tag.
So this is the equivalent of doing this.
It shows it's a little bit more succinct, because rather
than duplicating it over, it's fairly common
to just self-inclose like this.
In addition, something else that View tries to get you to do,
though, before we talk more about this,
is you'll notice that earlier I had this error, which is
from ESLint, in that we really try to recommend
that you use multi-word component names.
And the reason for that is because you never
know when the HTML spec is going to add something.
And they basically have, you know,
they get first dibs when it comes to one-word components.
So rather than basically run the risk of conflicting that,
what I might do instead is I might go,
I might call this like base counter.
This is like the counter to rule all components.
And so you'll notice here, though, that Volar,
hey, it says, I noticed you're refactoring some stuff.
And then you say, oh, what did you notice?
And it says, look, I noticed that inside of here,
you actually, like, it'll actually track the file path
of the things that it's related to, which is pretty cool.
So I can go ahead and apply that.
And now you'll see that inside of app.view,
it's gone ahead and actually renamed it correctly
inside of my imports, which is a nice optimization
that it does for us.
But once again, I really would like
to avoid the single-word naming.
So I'm just going to do that like that.
And then you'll see everything still works as expected.
But another thing that View does for you
in terms of extending upon HTML standards
is you might not like the Pascal case, which
is where you have the multi-word capitalized.
You might say, I would rather just do the standard kebab
case for HTML.
And believe it or not, that actually just works.
View will out of the box basically
allow you to convert between two cases
because it knows how to track the differences.
And so to say which one is better
depends a lot on the team that you're working with.
I would say in terms of pros and cons,
one of the nice things about the Pascal case
is that it becomes very evident that this is something very
specific to the app, that this is something custom.
Granted, if you're using a multi-word component,
that also does the job as well.
So this is kind of what you're used to in that regard.
You have a question?
With the inverse of that work, can you name the file kebab case?
I should be able to.
Let's give that a shot.
Oh, so the question was, can we name the file kebab case?
Like that.
And then, what did it change?
Well, here we go.
And notice that we have applied that, so we can apply that.
And then inside of here, we're good.
Inside of here, we can't do anything about it
because this is like an import.
And then I think that actually still works.
Yep, that still works.
The main thing about that is be consistent.
That's the only thing I ask.
Doesn't matter which one you choose, just be consistent.